בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is ע"ט, ayin tet, and
we pick up on ע"ח עמוד ב, ayin chet amud bet, staff
five lines before the lines get wide. We're dealing with a new
משנה. mishnah. The new משנה mishnah is no longer dealing with workers,
but it's dealing with rentals, and you rent a donkey. And the
first issue had to do that if you use it outside of
the terms of the agreement, then you are liable for what goes
wrong. That could be based on the principle of תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו
באונס. techilato bipshiah vesofo beones. If you start with a negligence, then
you are held liable for everything that comes afterwards. Or an alternative
that the גמרא Gemara dealt with is the position of Rabbi Meir
of כל המעביר על דעתו של בעל הבית נקרא גזלן, kol hamaveh
al daato shel baal habayit nikra gazlan, that you're not allowed to
violate the parameters of the owner. And that we sort of showed
other places where Rabbi Meir says that. But then we added to
it the idea that when you do violate the terms of the
agreement, you're considered like a thief, and basically you're fully liable for
anything that goes wrong, so it's not based on a concept of
negligence, it's based on a concept that you went against the terms
and now you are held liable. And now it's like you've taken
possession of the object. So those are the two ideas. Within the
issue of תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס, techilato bipshiah vesofo beones, you know,
is the point that if it really is
completely unrelated, then you would be exempt. That even with תחילתו בפשיעה
וסופו באונס, techilato bipshiah vesofo beones, the point is that we'd assume
it's an outcome of your original negligence. There's a presumption that it's
based on your original negligence. But in the case where it clearly
had nothing to do with that original negligence, then you actually would
be exempt. So that's not a complete liability, whereas the approach of
Rabbi Meir is a complete liability. Okay, so let's continue now. And
now we get to the second part of the משנה, mishnah, which
has to do with the owner's responsibility to replace the donkey if
something goes wrong because of the within the contract of the within
the length of the contract. השוכר את החמור
והבריקה. Hasocher es hachamor vehivrika. So again, this is like six lines
before the lines get wide. Somebody rents a donkey and it's והבריקה.
vehivrika. מאי והבריקה? Mai vehivrika? What's this והבריקה? vehivrika? הכא תרגימו, Hacha
targimu, here in בבל Bavel they translated it נהוריתא, nahurisa, where it
literally means like light, but רש"י Rashi says it's one of those
euphemistic phrases, רש"י Rashi says it means some type of a thing
wrong in the iris of the eye, so the donkey, you know,
the donkey's got some vision problem. The but the point is it's
not completely unusable. You can still use the donkey for carrying burdens,
but it's not as good as it was.
Okay. רבא אמר אבזקת. Rava amar avzeket. Right, it's always an interesting
question, like with your car company, you know, when you rent a
car and it got into an accident, when do they have to
replace it for you? Let's say it got a dent, but it's
still drivable. You know? So anyway, this donkey right now has a
dent, but he's still drivable. So the owner does not have to
replace it. That's what the משנה mishnah says, he says הרי שלך
לפניך. harei shelcha lefanecha. רבא אמר אבזקת. Rava amar avzeket. אבזקת Avzeket
is רש"י Rashi says it's a type of a worm. It's like
some worms got into its foot or its hoof or its leg
or something. Do donkeys have hoofs? No. Okay, whatever. Into its foot.
So you know, so the car, you know, whatever, the tire, some
problem with the tire, but it's still drivable. Okay, so you can
say הרי שלך לפניך. harei shelcha lefanecha. I don't have to replace
it. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, okay, רבא אמר אבזקת.
Rava amar avzeket. ההוא דאמר להו, Hahu deamar lehu, now that since
we mentioned אבזקת, avzeket, this like worm, there was a person that
said to people, אבזקת במילתא דמלכא. avzeket bemilsa demalka. There's a worm
that's eating in the
king's cloth, like the silk of the king, you know, the clothing.
I don't know, it's a type of it's not exactly a moth,
but something like that. So he wanted to warn them about this
danger to the king's clothing. אמר
להו במאי? Amar lehu bemai? In which part, in which of his,
you know, which of his clothing is it eating away at? בטלי
דכסף ובטלי דדהב. Betali dekesaf ubetali dedehav. In the garments of silver
or the garments of gold. So רש"י Rashi says this is like
not literally that he would wear silver or gold, but silver means
linen and gold means wool. I guess linen is has a silvery
color to it and wool he said they would dye a goldish
color. So אמר להו amru lei במאי? bemai?
בטלי
דכסף ובטלי דדהב. betali dekesaf ubetali dedehav. איכא דאמרי, Ika deamri, some
say בטלי דכסף אמר. betali dekesaf amar. He said in the silver
clothing, in the linen clothing. וקטלוהו, Vekatluha, and they killed him. Because
apparently this worm doesn't eat linen, so clearly he was lying. So
you know, you impugned the king's honor and it was a clear
lie, so you get killed. איכא דאמרי Ika deamri בטלי דדהב אמר,
betali dedehav amar, it was the gold one. ושבקוהו, Veshavkuha, and they
let him alone. Because that was possible. I don't know, nobody says
they rewarded him for alerting them to this danger.
או שנעשה אנגריא, Oshenasa angarya, אמר לו amar lo הרי שלך לפניך.
harei shelcha lefanecha. Now that's a case where it's like got a
dent in it but it's still drivable. But then you have the
case that it's אנגריא, angarya, which means it was seized by the
king, by the king's, you know, sort of servants, you know,
to appropriate it for the king's use. And the owner can still
say, fine, the donkey is still there. Now how can he say
that? I can't use it. The king's people have control over it.
So אמר רב, Amar Rav, לא שנו אלא באנגריא חוזרת. Lo shanu
ella be’angarya hozeret. That's only אנגריא Angarya that they're going to use
it for a little while and then they're going to return it.
Okay? Which is interesting. I still need this for the next three
days, right? I don't have use of it for the next three
days. But that's seen as like a temporary problem. Okay, and since
it's only a temporary problem, then it's not my the owner's responsibility
to replace it for you.
And do you recoup the rent for that time?
Yeah, it sounds like that. I know it's funny. We'll see in
a minute some other חשבון. heshbon. אבל אנגריא שאינו חוזרת, Aval angarya
she’eino hozeret, if they're not going to return it, חייב להעמיד לו
חמור, Hayav le’ha’amid lo hamor, then you have to replace it. Same
way the משנה Mishna says that if the donkey dies or breaks
a leg or something, you have to replace it. So if it's
been seized and that's the end of the story, you don't have,
obviously then the owner does have to replace it. That's what רב
Rav said. ושמואל אמר, U’shmuel amar, בין אנגריא חוזרת בין אנגריא שאינו
חוזרת, Bein angarya hozeret bein angarya she’eino hozeret, whether it's going to
be returned or not, there's times the owner doesn't have to replace
it even if it's not going to be returned. What are those
cases? אם בדרך הליכה נטלה, Im be’derech halicha nitla, if it was
taken in the way of going, אומר לו הרי שלך לפניך. Omer
lo harei shelcha lefanecha. I'll explain that in a minute. Then the
owner can say tough luck. ואם לאו בדרך הליכתה נטלה, Ve’im lav
be’derech halichata nitla, if it was not in its way of going,
חייב להעמיד לו חמור, Hayav le’ha’amid lo hamor, then he has to
replace it. So what does it mean the way of going? רש״י
Rashi describes a bizarre scenario where the king's troops would seize it
and they would use it to I don't know to schlep their
wares till they came onto the next victim. And when they came
to the next guy with a donkey, they'd give you your donkey
back and they'd take the next guy's donkey. So at least you
know it's equal equal like you know equal equal treatment of mistreatment
I guess you know. So that way, so okay, so that means
that now the funny thing is that sort of means it's always
חוזרת, hozeret, but it'll be חוזרת hozeret once they get up to
the next guy. So רש״י Rashi says the question of דרך הליכתה
derech halichata or לא דרך הליכתה lo derech halichata is: are they
taking the donkey in the direction you would be going with the
donkey anyway? So if they're taking the donkey in the direction you'd
be going, so yes you have to schlep after them, yes you're
not going to get it immediately back but eventually you will get
it back so therefore he says הרי שלך לפניך. harei shelcha lefanecha.
So that's a very strange scenario and at the end of the
day, it's really a variation of the idea of חוזרת. hozeret. תוספות
Tosafot says what at least to me seems like a better פשט
pshat that the point here is that what were the circumstances, and
this is consistent with other things the גמרא Gemara sometimes thinks about,
what were the circumstances under which they seized it. If they just
saw it walking on the way and they seized it, okay, then
that's seen as like that was your bad luck. Like you know
you happened to be on that street at that time, you the
renter, so in some sense of like מזל mazal or whatever, you
know the way in which sort of seen that some things like
you know are are I don't know predetermined isn't the right word,
but deserving of what happens, like your you know your luck brought
that about, it's somehow seen as due to you. You happened to
be walking on the street at that time, so if you don't
want to make it based on luck, somehow it has to be
because of of where you were, don't come to me the owner.
That's where you happened to be at that time, that's your bad
luck. Okay, so even if you're not going to even if you're
not going to get it back, okay, so I mean I know,
so anyway, but ואם לאו בדרך הליכתה ve’im lav be’derech halichata means
that they were in the town and they were going house to
house looking for a good donkey and they came onto your donkey,
so that's not seen as any choice that you made in anything
that results from you. That's just seen as a total אונס. ones.
Okay, and in that case, okay, your donkey's not usable, I have
to replace it. So תוספות Tosafot sort of makes it a question
of to what degree is it seen as a little bit your
your fault, fault is the wrong word, but a little bit you
know it resulted a little bit from something about you. All right?
Now the interesting thing is according to this that if it was
not your fault and they seized it, so remember שמואל Shmuel says
even if it's אנגריא חוזרת, angarya hozeret, even if they're going to
give it back to you two days later I have to replace
it for you. So תוספות Tosafot points out that this is an
interesting distinction. If it gets a dent, you know something in its
eye, something in its leg but it's still usable, I don't have
to do anything, right, because it's still usable. But if it gets
seized even if it just gets seized for for a day, if
it's if it's considered to be not not due to you in
any reason, right, then I have to replace it at least for
that day. Give me give me a loaner. I need it for
this day. Who cares I'm going to get it back tomorrow? Today
I need it. So it's different than the case with the bad
eye where you can still use it. So this is I really
like the approach of שמואל. Shmuel. שמואל Shmuel says if completely unusable,
so if it's not this guy's fault in any way, you know
not seen as his fault, the owner has to immediately replace it.
If it is seen as his fault, he happened to be in
the wrong place at the wrong time but that's seen as his
fault, okay, then the owner does not have to replace it even
if it's even if he'll never get it back. Okay? So it's
an interesting extreme within שמואל. Shmuel.
And he can't just tell him look forget about today, too much
of a hassle, let me just extend your rental for another day.
That's an interesting question. I guess it depends on how much the
guy says that he does or doesn't have that choice. Okay, so
let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this, תא
שמע. ta shema. מיתיבי, meitivei, I'll ask you
on this. השוכר את החמור והבריקה. Ha’socher et ha’hamor ve’hivrika. We have
a
ברייתא. braita. Deal with it. Okay, מתה *Meisa* or
שנאנסה אנגריא *shenastasa angarya*,
if it dies or was seized by the king, by right, so
then there's no way you can use it, חייב להעמיד לו חמור
*chayav l'ha'amid lo chamor*. You have to replace it. So this ברייתא
braisa *Baraita* against the משנה Mishnah *Mishna* has a different ruling about
the being seized by the king, and it says it has to
be replaced. Our משנה Mishnah *Mishna* says it doesn't have to be
replaced. So how do you reconcile the ברייתא braita *Baraita* with the
משנה Mishnah. *Mishna*? בשלמא לרב לא קשיא *Bishlama l'Rav lo kashya*, for
רב Rav *Rav* it's not difficult. כאן באנגריא חוזרת *Kan b'angarya chozeres*,
the משנה Mishnah *Mishna* that says you don't have to replace it
is when it's going to be returned. כאן באנגריא שאינה חוזרת *Kan
b'angarya she'eina chozeres*, the ברייתא baraita *Baraita* that says the owner has
to replace it is when it won't be returned. אלא Ela, לשמואל
קשיא *Ela l'Shmuel kashya*, for שמואל Shmuel, *Shmuel* it's difficult. וכי תימא
לשמואל נמי לא קשיא *V'chi teima l'Shmuel nami lo kashya*, one minute,
שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* can use this distinction. כאן שבדרך הילוכה נטלה *Kan
sheb'derech hilucha nitla*, when it was seized because where you happened to
be, then it's your fault, it doesn't have to be replaced. כאן
שלא בדרך הילוכה נטלה *Kan shelo b'derech hilucha nitla*, the ברייתא *Baraita*
is when it was seized and it wasn't where you happened to
be, they were searching around for something. So in that case it's
not your fault and it does have to be replaced. So that's
a nice way of reconciling it, that's the split that שמואל Shmuel.
*Shmuel* makes. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says but what? הא מדקתני סיפא
*Ha mideka tani seifa*, you can't say that that's what's going on
in the first part of the ברייתא *Baraita* when it says it
has to be replaced, because the end of the ברייתא *Baraita* makes
that distinction in the name of a רבי שמעון בן אלעזר *Rabi
Shimon ben Elazar*. Here's what the end of the ברייתא *Baraita* says:
רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר *Rabi Shimon ben Elazar omer*, אם בדרך
הילוכה נטלה *im b'derech hilucha nitla*, now you know where שמואל Shmuel
*Shmuel* got it from, if it was seized where you happened to
be walking, אומר לו הרי שלך לפניך *omer lo harei shelcha lefanecha*,
the owner can say, "Ha! Tough luck, you brought it on yourself."
ואם לאו *Ve'im lav*, but if it wasn't that circumstance, חייב להעמיד
לו חמור *chayav l'ha'amid lo chamor*, he has to replace it. So
it's רבי שמעון בן אלעזר *Rabi Shimon ben Elazar* that makes the
distinction of what were the circumstances of its being seized. מכלל דתנא
קמא *Michlal d'Tanna Kamma* for the first תנא *Tanna*, לא שנא ליה
*lo shani lei*, he doesn't care, he always thinks you have to
replace it. So that's a difficulty on שמואל *Shmuel* because at least
the first תנא *Tanna* who's the authoritative voice says it always has
to be replaced. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אמר לך שמואל
*Amar lach Shmuel*, לאו מכלל דרבי שמעון בן אלעזר דקאי כוותי *lav
michlal d'Rabi Shimon ben Elazar d'ka'ei k'vasi*? Okay, so the first תנא
*Tanna* disagrees with me. I at least have רבי שמעון בן אלעזר
*Rabi Shimon ben Elazar*. What's he, chopped liver? So I'm normally like
רבי שמעון בן אלעזר *Rabi Shimon ben Elazar*. I like what רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר *Rabi Shimon ben Elazar* says, that's the one that
I think that he's correct, that that's the distinction. איבעית אימא *Iba'is
eima*, and if you want, because it's always better to have the
more authoritative voice go like you, איבעית אימא *iba'is eima*, כולה רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר היא *kulah Rabi Shimon ben Elazar hi*. The whole
ברייתא *Baraita* is רבי שמעון בן אלעזר *Rabi Shimon ben Elazar*. וחסורי
מחסרא והכי קתני *V'chasuri mechasra v'hachi katani*, it's missing some words, meaning
it really means to clarify, the last statement of רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר *Rabi Shimon ben Elazar* is really clarifying the initial statement, not
disagreeing with it. השוכר את החמור והבריקה או שנשתטה אומר לו הרי
שלך לפניך *Hasocher es hachamor vehivrika o shenishtata omer lo harei shelcha
lefanecha*. So if it got, you know, went a little crazy or
got something in the eyes, you say you can still use it.
מתה או שנאנסה אנגריא חייב להעמיד לו חמור *Meisa o shenestasa angarya
chayav l'ha'amid lo chamor*. If it dies or it's seized, it can't
be used, you have to replace it. במה דברים אמורים *Bamei devarim
amurim*, when is this true? שלא בדרך הילוכה נטלה *Shelo b'derech hilucha
nitla*, when it was seized not because where you happened to be
walking. אבל נטלה בדרך הילוכה *Aval nitla b'derech hilucha*, if it was
seized where it happened to be walking, אומר לו הרי שלך לפניך
*omer lo harei shelcha lefanecha*, then the owner can say tough luck,
you brought it on yourself, it was your bad luck, I'm not
going to replace it. דברי רבי שמעון בן אלעזר *Divrei Rabi Shimon
ben Elazar*, that's the words of רבי שמעון בן אלעזר *Rabi Shimon
ben Elazar*, שהיה רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר *shehaya Rabi Shimon ben
Elazar omer*, because רבי שמעון בן אלעזר *Rabi Shimon ben Elazar* used
to say, אם בדרך הילוכה נטלה אומר לו הרי שלך לפניך *im
b'derech hilucha nitla omer lo harei shelcha lefanecha*, if it was where
it was walking you can say that was your bad luck, tough
luck, I'm not going to replace it, ואם לאו חייב להעמיד לו
חמור *ve'im lav chayav l'ha'amid lo chamor*. Okay, you have to replace
it. Fine. So we got שמואל *Shmuel*'s distinction. Now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* continues, four lines from the top on עמוד ט *amud tes*.
ומי מצית מוקמת לה כרבי שמעון בן אלעזר *U'mi matsis mokmas lah
k'Rabi Shimon ben Elazar*? How can you say this is going like
רבי שמעון בן אלעזר *Rabi Shimon ben Elazar*? והקתני רישא *V'hakatani reisha*,
השוכר את החמור והבריקה או שנשתטה *Hasocher es hachamor vehivrika o shenishtata*,
the beginning of the ברייתא *Baraita* says, the ברייתא *Baraita* we just
quoted, that
if it got this bad vision or it went a little crazy,
you say הרי שלך לפניך *harei shelcha lefanecha*, ואילו רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר אומר *v'ilu Rabi Shimon ben Elazar omer*, but we have a
different ברייתא *Baraita* apparently of רבי שמעון בן אלעזר *Rabi Shimon ben
Elazar* who says, השוכר את החמור לרכוב עליה Hasocher et hachamor lirkov
aleha. *Hasocher es hachamor lirkov aleha*, if you rent the donkey not
to carry your wares but for riding purposes, והבריקה או שנשתטה *vehivrika
o shenishtata*, and it got this bad eye or it went crazy,
חייב להעמיד לו חמור *chayav l'ha'amid lo chamor*. You have to replace
it. So the ברייתא *Baraita* which makes the distinction that at the
end of the ברייתא *Baraita* רבי שמעון בן אלעזר *Rabi Shimon ben
Elazar* makes the distinction between whether it was seized as it was
walking or not, and we're trying to say according to שמואל *Shmuel*
that the whole ברייתא *Baraita* holds of that distinction, but the beginning
of the ברייתא *Baraita* says you don't have to replace it when
it goes crazy, but רבי שמעון בן אלעזר *Rabi Shimon ben Elazar*
says you do have to replace it when it goes crazy.
So how does that work? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no,
the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says, אמר רבא בר רב Rav הונא לרכוב
עליה שאני *Amar Raba bar Rav Huna lirkov aleha shani*. No, no,
no. That רבי שמעון בן אלעזר *Rabi Shimon ben Elazar* is very
specific. When you
rent it to ride on it, it has to be replaced. So
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says, look at רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, why does it
matter? לרכוב שאני *Lirkov shani*, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says, שמא תפול תחתיו
בגשר או שתשליכנו באחת הפחתים *shema tipol tachtav b'gesher o shetashlichenu b'achas
hap'chasim*, the פחתים *p'chasim*, right? So it's like if I'm going to
be riding it, it's sort of like my car example, right? So
it's like I don't want to ride in a dangerous vehicle. It's
one thing if you say, "Alright, it's a little crazy, it can
still carry your wares." wares. Right? Worst thing that happens is it
slips and you have to pick it up again, okay?
And break your expensive wares.
Well, we'll get to break your expensive wares in a minute. But
for riding on it, I'm not going to take the risk that
it's going to slip. So for if it's intended for riding purposes,
now it's unusable. That makes a lot of sense. So then the
גמרא Gemara makes the next logical conclusion, which is what Michael said.
So the גמרא Gemara. says,
אמר רב פפא וכלי זכוכית כרכוב עליו דמי. Amar Rav Pappa uchelei
zechochis keerchavo alav dami.
If you're carrying glasswares, it's like you rented it to ride upon
it, right? So any type of a thing where no, I'm sorry,
this is an unacceptable risk. It'll damage me, it'll damage my wares,
then okay, it has to be replaced. But if you're let's say
you got sacks of grain on it. All right, got sacks of
grain, big deal, it might slip, so it'll take you five more
minutes to get it back up, big deal. Okay. So now the
גמרא Gemara. says like this: אמר רבה בר הונא אמר רב השוכר
את החמור לרכוב עליה ומתה לו בחצי הדרך. Amar Rabba bar Huna
amar Rav hasocher es hachamor lirkov aleha umeisa lo bachatzi haderech. Now
we're going to get into like these really what I consider like
fun cases, which is similar to discussions on what if the workers
back out in the middle of the day? Right? So in a
sense that was our discussion, what if the donkey dies in the
middle of the day, right, it has to be replaced, but now
we're going to get to more complicated situations like that about whose
responsibility is it.
Okay, so
השוכר את החמור לרכוב עליה ומתה לו בחצי הדרך. hasocher es hachamor
lirkov aleha umeisa lo bachatzi haderech. It dies in the middle
of the
way. נותן לו שכרו של חצי הדרך. Nosin lo secharo shel chatzi
haderech.
So that's your answer, pro-rate. Michael pays me for half of for
half of it. So that's a nice deal for me, I don't
have to replace it and I get the you know I get
the half of the payment. Okay. נותן לו שכרו של חצי הדרך.
Nosin lo secharo shel chatzi haderech. ואין לו עליו אלא
תרעומת. Ve'ein lo alav ela teroumes. And I, and Michael, okay, he
can complain, I'm here, you told me I needed to get all
the way, you know, I rented it from New York to Florida
and I only wound up in what's a middle state? Georgia. Okay,
I knew Georgia, I was thinking of one a little higher. What's
higher than Georgia? South Carolina! I only got to South Carolina. So
is my geographic knowledge... anyway, I only got to South Carolina. So
what do you mean, okay, pay you half? I don't want to
pay anything! I didn't get to where I needed to go. Right?
So it's you need to replace the donkey for me. That's what
we were saying before. But this is a very seems to be
a very different approach. You have to pay me half, you got
it halfway, and I... the rest is just complaints you have. Okay.
ואין לו עליו אלא תרעומת. Ve'ein lo alav ela teroumes. So גמרא
Gemara says, היכי דמי? Heichi dami? What's the case? אי דשכיח לאגורי,
Ee deshchiach le'agurei,
if now Michael in South Carolina can easily rent another U-Haul,
okay, they're readily available. So תרעומת מאי עבידתיה, teroumes mai avidteih, why
does he have a complaint? Take, you know, you only paid half,
take the rest of the money, go rent another U-Haul. Obviously, it
might cost more and it's a huge שלעפ schlepp anyway to transfer
the whole thing. Okay, we'll see. אי דלא שכיח לאגורי, Ee delo
shchiach le'agurei, if there are no U-Hauls
available, so אגרא בעי למיתב ליה? agra ba'ei lemisiv lei? He has
to pay me? Like what are you talking about? He didn't get
out of it what he wanted to get out of it. He
didn't want to wind up in South Carolina, he wanted to wind
up in Atlanta... I mean in Florida. And I'm the one that
has to replace it for him. So what sense does any of
this make? So let's take a look. ולעולם, Ve'olam, version one, דלא
שכיח לאגורי. delo shchiach le'agurei.
No U-Hauls to be rented. All right, so what's going on here?
ומשום דאמר ליה, Umishum de'amar lei, because I can say to Michael,
אילו בעית למיתי עד הכא לאו אגרא בעית
למיתב? elu be'isa lemisei ad hacha lav agra be'isa lemisiv? So look
Michael, if you had wanted to go to South Carolina, that's what
it would have cost you. So I got you all the way
to South Carolina! So what are you complaining about? So the question
is, what the heck does it mean what is he complaining about?
He didn't want to go to South Carolina. So look at תוספות.
Tosafos. תוספות Tosafos says, אילו עד הכא בעית למיתי לאו אגרא בעית
למיתב? elu ad hacha be'isa lemisei lav agra be'isa lemisiv? So תוספות
תימא דהתם מיד לאו עד הכא בעי למיתי, Tosafos teima de'hasam miyad
lav ad hacha ba'ei lemisei,
he wasn't going to South Carolina. So למה יתן לו שכר? lama
yiten lo sechar? Why should he pay me anything? This is not
what he wanted. ויש לומר, Ve'yesh lomar, and he remember there are
no U-Hauls available to finish the trip, right? So תוספות, Tosafos, because
this is so crazy, תוספות Tosafos has to reinterpret the case. And
here's what he says.
דהא דקאמר לעולם דלא שכיח לאגורי, De'hada kamer le'olam delo shchiach le'agurei,
when it says that there are no U-Hauls available, היינו לפי אותן
הדמים שהשכיר מזה. hainu lefi osan hadamim she'hisakir mizeh.
That means that he can't buy a U-Haul at the same rate,
rent a U-Haul. אבל בטפי פורתא ימצא להשכיר. Aval betfei purta yimtza
le'haskir.
So that's not at all what the גמרא Gemara said, but it
says, okay, Michael can find a U-Haul it's a little more expensive.
It's not $25 a day, it's $30 a day. והרי נהנה במה
שבא עד כאן. Vaharei ne'enah bema sheba ad kan. And look... I
got you halfway, and now you're only going to rent the U-Haul.
Yes, it's true it'll be thirty dollars a day, but you're only
going to have to rent it for half the journey. לכך נותן
לו חצי שכרו, Lechach noten lo chatzi secharo, therefore you have to
pay me. ואין צריך לפחות המשכיר משכרו מה שזה נותן עתה יותר
מעט מכאן ואילך. Ve-ein tzarich lifchot hamaskir mischaro mah shezeh noten atah
yoter me-at mikan ve-eilach. Now, that's
now that's a little bit weird. Okay, maybe, maybe you can rent
this so fine, I should deduct from you the difference between the
thirty dollars a day and whatever, you know, the extra you're going
to be paying. No, I don't have to. Why not? כיון דהוא
אנוס Keivan dehu anus
because look, it was nobody's fault. So you know, you have in
a way you have to suffer a little bit the bad luck
together with me, since at the end of the day you're going
to be able to get it done. It's only going to be
and it goes
to the point where it's like my choice to back out and
your choice to find.
Yeah, although then it also gets to the question what happens if
there's an אונס, ones, which we dealt with before, which we'll get
to again. It's a hard interpretation. תוספות Tosafot is dealing with a
very difficult גמרא. Gemara He tries to limit the case, but even
within the limited case, first of all, how much is a lot
more and how much is not a lot more in terms of
the expense, right? And even so, you know, it's still a little
funny. But the תוספות Tosafot's point is that you know what do
you do when it's nobody's fault? Who has to suffer the consequences
of that? So his way of reading of choosing to read the
גמרא Gemara is that well, if it's only a little bit of
loss and at the end of the day you're getting your journey
done, like don't come complain then why should I suffer? You might
as well be the one who suffers. Okay, now he has another
version because that's you know because again he's just trying to give
ways to make sense of the גמרא. Gemara אי נמי, Ei nami,
says תוספות, Tosafot, כגון שיוכל למכור סחורתו במקום שמת החמור. kegon sheyuchal
limkor sechorato bemakom shemet hachamor. You know, Michael, you could sell your
stuff there in South Carolina. You don't have to sell your wares
in Florida. וירוויח בה. Veyarviach bah. ויש סוחרים הרבה שמביאים סחורה מעד
כאן. Ve-yesh socharim harbeh shemevi'im sechorah mi-ad kan. So look, I know,
I know you were intending to sell it in Florida, but there's
an equal opportunity in South Carolina. You know, hustle a little bit,
you'll be able to sell your wares here. So that already is
not a bad answer, right? It's like you know, he's doing it
not because he's moving to Florida, he's doing it to make a
business, and I could say, look, I got you here, it's an
equivalent market, I know it wasn't the market you were expecting, but
nevertheless, you know, it's a you can sell your stuff here as
well. Alright, anyway, that's one way of interpreting it, but you know,
it really like the תוספות Tosafot wasn't in the גמרא. Gemara The
גמרא Gemara sort of made it sound like in all cases, hey
I got you halfway, you know, it's sort of it's almost like
some of this thing makes me think and we'll get cases like
this, you know, you hire a cab to take you like you
know to the you know to I don't know the you know
downtown and he brings you to the upper west side and he
says, I gotta go take care of some of my own business,
get out here, but pay me half the fare because I got
you halfway. You
know, so anyway, alright, I mean sometimes it's not so bad, you
get another cab, you jump into the
subway, right? Alright, anyway, depends on what your alternatives are at that
stage. Alright, let's say he lets you out in the South Bronx,
not exactly the same thing, right? So he says like this. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara has another question. Fine, let's assume for
whatever reason that he's not replacing the donkey and for whatever reason
because he got you halfway you have to pay him half. But
why isn't he replacing the donkey, what happened to what our משנה
Mishnah. taught? So the גמרא Gemara says that. Okay,
היכי דמי, Heichi dami, what's the case? אי דאמר ליה חמור סתם.
Ei de-amar leh chamor stam. Now we're going to see a distinction
that wasn't in the משנה Mishna but is critical to the משנה.
When I rented Michael a donkey, okay, if I said I'm renting
you a donkey without any specification, okay, חייב להעמיד לו חמור אחר.
chayav le-ha'amid lo chamor acher.
That's what our משנה says. I said I'd rent you a donkey
for the week. I didn't say this donkey. If this donkey dies,
I have to I have to find another donkey to rent you.
I contracted to rent you a donkey for the week. אי דאמר
ליה חמור זה, Ei de-amar leh chamor zeh, if I said I'm
renting you this donkey, okay, so now I still might have to
replace it. Why? This gets back to a רש"י Rashi I mentioned
on the משנה. That means you still have a right to a
donkey, but based somehow from this donkey. What would what would that
mean? אם יש בדמיה ליקח יקח. Im yesh bidmeyah likach yikach.
If this donkey still can I can sell the dead carcass and
buy another donkey, that's still you've had this donkey rented, right? So
I've rented this donkey. It's true it's dead, it's a dead donkey,
but I still have it rented for the week, which means that
I should be it should be, you know, you should sell the
dead carcass and replace and at least I should be able to
use that because that's seen as like a continuation of the first
donkey. Alright, so the so then that would be the obligation.
Like, you know, like I rented the Porsche, it breaks, you know,
you sell it for parts and then you get something like a
Camry, whatever.
Exactly. Okay, okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
so the גמרא Gemara says like this,
oh a minute, right, so then still why does Michael pay me
half? I should if I said just a donkey I should have
to replace it. Even if I say this donkey, I should have
to replace it if I can buy another donkey with the carcass
with the proceeds of the dead one. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, the most obvious case is that you can't buy another donkey
with the proceeds of the dead one, right? לא צריכה כשאין
בדמיה ליקח. Lo tzerichah keshein bidmeyah likach. So you can't buy one,
you can't buy. So you said this donkey, it's dead, you can't
buy a new one with the proceeds, so the owner doesn't have
to replace it and then Michael has to pay me half of
it because he got halfway. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute.
So the גמרא Gemara says
יש בדמיה לשכור ישכור. yesh bidameha lischor yiscor. So גמרא Gemara says
fine, go buy another donkey, but I still said to Michael I
would rent him the donkey for the week. So here's what we
can do: even if I said this donkey, sell this donkey, use
the money for Michael to get a rental for the rest of
the week, okay? So at least that's like he has this donkey
asset, which includes the proceeds of this donkey, and let him at
least use a- I- rather than saying our relationship ends here, pay
me for half the journey, no, he has a right to this
donkey for the week. So sell the carcass, use the proceeds for
a rental in order to use in order to get it for
the rest of the week. So the גמרא Gemara says, so that's
a good question. So the גמרא Gemara says רב לטעמיה. Rav letamei.
רב Rav, goes according to his reasoning. דאמר רב לא מכלינן קרנא.
da'amar Rav lo mechalinan karna. We do not eat into the
principal.
When I said to you this donkey and I have a responsibility
to you for the week, if I say a donkey, I have
to find a donkey for the rest of the week. This donkey,
my responsibility to you is only vis-a-vis this donkey. But if the
donkey dies, it's one thing to tell me buy another one and
let Michael use the other one for the rest of the week,
because at least I'm not losing any of my assets, or the
asset what I lost was when it died, but after it's dead
I don't lose any more of my assets, right? Might be that
I took that proceeds, I added my own money, I bought a
new donkey, I reinvested it, and now Michael still gets it for
the rest of the week. But my responsibility to Michael now is
like it was before. Let him use my asset, but it doesn't
actually make me lose my assets. You know, but if you say
sell the proceeds and use the money to rent a donkey for
Michael, then I'm not just letting him use my assets, I'm actually
depreciating, you know, it's cutting into my assets, my responsibility to Michael.
So my responsibility does not go that far. My responsibility to him
is to let him use things that I own for the duration
of the week. It's not to actually take from my principal
and lose my principal in order that he can have a donkey.
All right, so that's why he ends up not being able to
rent it to someone else. Right, so I'm not benefiting, but it's
not actually cutting into principal. No, it's lack of profit is not
the same as loss, right? It's not cutting into my principal.
He sell the donkey to rent to someone else? Once it's dead,
though, what principal is there?
The principal is the money that now the dead donkey is worth.
He should the renter should give that to the owner.
Right, sell it, sell it, use that money to buy a new
donkey, let Michael use the donkey for the week, okay? And then
he's getting the profit off of that principal, but he's not cutting
into the principal.
But what if it's not sufficient to rent another donkey? Then what
is- is the renter supposed to sell that donkey and give that
money to the owner? What it was worth?
One more time, what was the question?
If the money's not enough to buy another donkey? Yes. So then
he's supposed to rent one, right?
No, that's what's being debated.
So in other words, if it's not- if it's enough, he should
rent a donkey. Right, that way he can return it to the
owner and if the new- he should buy a new donkey.
Buy a new donkey and
return it to the owner in the end. Right. And if it's
not enough, then he's supposed to do what, sell the dead donkey
and give that money to the owner?
Yes, or the owner sells the donkey. Yes, exactly. And then right,
and then the relationship terminates there. That would be the case. Now
רש"י Rashi interest- importantly רש"י Rashi says that the idea that you
want to retain- have the owner retain the principal would mean that
the owner might have to dig into his pocket, but he still
retains the principal. So if you look at רש"י לא מכלינן קרנא,
Rashi lo mechalinan karna, about ten lines from the- from where the
lines get
narrow, רש"י Rashi says וכי תנן במתניתין חייב להעמיד לו חמור אחר
היכא דמיתה ועודו בבית בעלים דמוסיף ולוקח חמור. vechi tnan bamatnitin chayav
lehamid lo chamor acher heicha demisa veodu beveit baalim demosif velokeach chamor.
You dig into your profit- pocket. This is a dead donkey, it's
only worth a hundred dollars. Donkeys goes for a thousand dollars. I
have to take nine hundred dollars out of my pocket and buy
a new donkey and then Michael use the donkey for the rest
of the week. But that is not cutting into my principal because
at the end of the day I have
a thousand dollar donkey. Okay? ולא קאי הנאה למכרה להוציא את דמיה
לשכור אחר לא. velo ka'i hana'ah limkora lehotzi et dameha lischor acher
lo. But that actually to- the hundred dollars should be lost to
me and it's going to be going out in rental fees, that
is not my responsibility. Okay, so that's רב's Rav. explanation. So according
to רב, Rav. that would be the case where the owner doesn't
have to replace it, where- is that another one can't be bought
and you don't have a responsibility to actually use the pro- use
the money to rent where you're actually losing your asset. That's according
to רב. Rav, So now the גמרא Gemara. says like
this: רב לטעמיה דאמר לא מכלינן קרנא דאתמר השוכר את חמור ומתה.
Rav letamei da'amar lo mechalinan karna de'itmar hasocher et hachamor umeta. You
rented a donkey and it died. ומתה לחצי הדרך. umeta lachatzi haderech.
אמר רב, amar Rav, and it's presumably he says חמור זה, chamor
ze, you only had a deal with this donkey, you didn't have
a general responsibility for a donkey. So אמר רב מיסה דמיה ליקח.
amar Rav misa dameha likach. If there's enough money to buy a
replacement, buy a replacement. לשכור אל ישכור, liskor al yiskor, but to
rent, don't, you can't rent. You can't cut into the principal. ושמואל
אמר: אף לשכור ישכור. uShmuel amar af liskor yiskor. No, no, no,
even if there's money there to rent. So Michael is stuck in
South Carolina, I'm not around because רש"י makes it sound like, if
I'm around then maybe there's always enough money, let me add my
own assets and buy a new one. Okay, so maybe I always
have to replace it even if it's a חמור זה, chamor ze,
I have to add my assets and now buy a new one
and now let him use it. But he's in South Carolina, he
has to make the decision. Okay, so he's not going to put
out his own money to buy a new donkey. And according to
שמואל, שמואל says actually he can use the proceeds of this to
rent and cut into my assets to replace, you know, to allow
him to use it for the rest of the week. Okay,
ושמואל אמר uShmuel amar: אף לשכור ישכור. af liskor yiskor. במאי קמיפלגי?
b'mai kamifligi? What are they debating? רב סבר: Rav savar: לא מחלינן
קרנא, lo mechalinan karna, we don't cut into the owner's assets. ושמואל
אמר מחלינן קרנא, uShmuel amar mechalinan karna, we do cut into the
owner's assets. Okay, מיתיבי. meitvei. Let's see how this plays out in
other scenarios when somebody has a responsibility and he wasn't, and he
was intending it only to be a usage, will he ever have
to cut, dig into his own pocket and actually cut into his
own assets if circumstances change? Let's take a look. יבש אילן ונקצץ.
yavesh ilan v'niktzatz.
Now here, Michael left, so here Gloria now has a, has a
relationship, I borrowed money from Gloria and Gloria now has rights, remember
the whole case of a משכנתא. mashkona. She is in possession of
this tree in my yard, this gorgeous אתרוג esrog tree I've got.
Okay, or apple tree. And she's getting all the benefits from it
for the next few years while I'm waiting to pay her back.
And however we address the ריבית ribbis issue, we address the ריבית
ribbis issue. That's based on the earlier פרק. perek. All right, so
basically she has the right to the fruit of the tree for
the year. For now, do you ever, now you understand that this
is exactly parallel to the donkey. I own the donkey, you have
the right to the usage of the donkey for the week. I
own the tree, Gloria has the right to the fruit, the profit
of the tree for the year. All right, so that's the case.
Now what happens? In the, during the year, יבש אילן ונקצץ. yavesh
ilan v'niktzatz. It's dried up or got cut down. And Gloria's like,
whoa, I had the right for a whole year of fruit. So
what are we going to do? So שניהם אסורים בו. shneichem assurim
bo. Neither of us, now the most obvious way we can get
some money out of this is to sell the tree for wood.
Okay, but if you sell the tree for wood, there goes my
whole asset. So can we sell it for wood to give Gloria
the profit she would have made off the tree? So it says
no. She can't sell it because she's cutting into my asset. I
can't sell it because Gloria could say I don't care if you
give me all the proceeds
of the wood, I would have maybe gotten more had the stuff
been a tree and continued to give me profit or whatever. So
neither, either side can stop the other side from selling it. All
right, so what do you do?
כיצד יעשה? keitzad ya'aseh? What do you do? ילקח בו קרקע. yilkach
bo karka. Yes, sell it, but don't just sell it and then
give the money to Gloria. Sell it and then buy another plot
of land. והוא אוכל פירות. v'hu ochel peiros. And then Gloria continues
to eat the fruit. Now of course the question is, like with
the donkey case, you might not get an equivalent type of a
tree for that. I have to now add my own money to
make up the difference. Like some important points are missing here. Okay,
but let's assume yes. So anyway, this seems very much like רב.
Rav We can replace a principal and let the person continue to
benefit from the principal, but we can't cut into the assets itself.
Looks like you want to ask a question, Zerach?
Processing it? Okay. Like imagine you're...
there's no way you're going to be able to buy a piece
of...
Right. Right. It's actually funny that he even says buy land, because
I presumably still own the land, I just have to buy a
new tree. But maybe you don't buy a tree and plant it,
you have to buy a whatever. So presumably I might have to
actually add to the principal. Okay, so it says like this: כיצד
יעשה ילקח בו קרקע והוא אוכל פירות. keitzad ya'aseh yilkach bo karka
v'hu ochel peiros. והכא כיון דמטי יובל. v'hacha keivan d'mati yovel. So
now the question is, so now the first part of the ברייתא
seems like a good support for רב, Rav that it's a case
where you don't cut into the principal. But the גמרא's Gemara got
a problem. The גמרא Gemara says even when you buy a plot
of land, you're cutting into the principal. How am I cutting into
the principal by buying me a plot of land? So the גמרא
Gemara says well, let's, we're going to assume that יובל yovel is
in, is in effect. I don't know why we're going to assume
that. והכא, v'hacha, so if יובל yovel is in effect, what happens
when I buy... I buy this plot of land off of Jenna
so that now Gloria can eat the fruit. Okay, what's going to
happen now when the יובל yovel runs around, comes around? Jenna's going
to get it back. So I now actually, even what we're doing
now for me to satisfy my responsibility to Gloria is going to
cut into my principal. That money that I gave for that plot
of land and that whatever, that's going to be lost to me
because the plot of land is eventually going to be lost to
me. So the גמרא Gemara says והכא דכי מטי יובל קהדרא ארעא
למרה וקא כליא קרנא. v'hacha d'ki mati yovel kahadra ara l'marei v'ka
kalya karna. And it's going to go to waste, so you see
that at least we are prepared to, for me to live up
to my responsibility to cut into my principal. So the גמרא Gemara
says,
but why isn't that the case with the
dead tree itself?
With the land originally?
The land originally that might have been my own inherited land, whatever,
I wouldn't have gone back to anybody. No, but the question is
how's that different than the tree? Because you're not letting me sell
the tree, so clearly there is a concern of cutting into the
principal. So we'll see in the גמרא. Gemara הכא במאי עסקינן דזבנה
לשישים שני. hacha b’mai askinan d’zavneh l’shishim shani.
It's a case where we avoided the יובל. yovel. I bought it
with Jenna and I explicitly said, stipulated, I for a sixty-year purchase.
So יובל yovel won't revert it. Why not? דאמר רב חסדא אמר
רב קטינא מנין למוכר שדהו לשישים שנה שאינה חוזרת ביובל? d’amar Rav
Chisda amar Rav Katina minayin l’mocher sadeh l’shishim shana she’eina chozeres b’yovel?
How do you know if you sell your plot for sixty years,
and they give the example sixty years which means a יובל yovel
will definitely hit in the middle, that it still won't go back
during the יובל? yovel? שנאמר והארץ לא תמכר לצמיתות. shene’emar v’ha’aretz lo
timacher l’tzmitut. The land shall not be sold into perpetuity. And therefore,
and the יובל yovel is a corrective for it being sold into
perpetuity. So it says, מי שאין שם יובל נצמתת יש שם יובל
אינה נצמתת. mi she’ein sham yovel nitzmetet yesh sham yovel eina nitzmetet.
So something where if there wasn't a יובל, yovel, it would be
sold into perpetuity, מי שאין שם יובל, mi she’ein sham yovel, if
it weren't יובל yovel it would be sold into perpetuity, therefore when
the יובל yovel comes around, that reverses the sale. Okay, so the
יובל yovel works on something that otherwise would have been a sale
for perpetuity. אבל יצאה זאת aval yatza zot to exclude a case
of sixty years, שאף על פי שאין שם יובל אינה נצמתת. she’af
al pi she’ein sham yovel eina nitzmetet. That it's already solved the
problem. It was not being sold into perpetuity anyway, so יובל yovel
doesn't affect it. Of course, which raises an interesting question, so I'll
sell it to you for ten thousand years, right? At what point
is it considered צמיתות? tzmitus? How about a hundred years? You know,
that's what they thought about Hong Kong. A hundred years, that'll never
come around. So eventually a hundred years comes around, right? So anyway,
okay, but for whatever, that's why maybe it's sixty. Sixty is like
reasonable within a person's lifetime or something. Anyway, the point is, so
therefore it’s not, the money isn't lost, you avoided the יובל. yovel.
Of course the גמרא Gemara asks the next obvious question. The גמרא
Gemara says, סוף סוף כי מטו שישים שנין כהדרא למרה. sof sof
ki matu shishim shanin kahadra l’marei. Okay,
you avoided the יובל, yovel, but you're still going to have to
give the land back after sixty years. So מיכלא קא כליא קרנא,
michla ka kalya karna, so you're still losing your original investment. אלא
הכא במאי עסקינן בזמן שאין יובל נוהג. ela hacha b’mai askinan b’zman
she’ein yovel noheig. Thank you. Okay, it's, we're not dealing with the
time of the יובל. yovel. There's a debate in the ראשונים Rishonim
whether the יובל yovel applied rabbinically during the second בית המקדש. Beit
Hamikdash. The most obvious thing to say is that it did not
apply during the period of the second בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. So
it's even a bizarre question that the גמרא Gemara was assuming that
that was the case, that there was יובל. yovel. There's no יובל,
yovel, so you know, it’s בזמן הזה, b’zman hazeh, so it's a,
that's, that's נישט nisht issue. הכי נמי
מסתברא, hachi nami mistavra, you know that makes sense to say, and
therefore this ברייתא is actually proving that you don't cut into the
principal and you buy the land and that's not cutting into the
principal. די סלקא דעתך בזמן שיובל נוהג ומכלינן קרנא, d’ee salka da’atach
b’zman she’yovel noheig u’machalnan karna,
if we were talking that there was a יובל yovel and it
was okay with buying land even though it would have to go
back and it was okay with cutting into the principal, if that's
true, what's the difference, why was it okay of cutting into the
principal with the buying of the land but it wasn't okay of
cutting into the principal with selling the wood? Why can't Gloria just
say, look, if you're going to cut into your principal, buy land
that's going to revert, might as well just sell the wood and
give me that money. So no, no, no, we're only going to
buy the land, not what's the difference? So the גמרא Gemara says,
נצצהו וצביה ונשקלי, nitzcheih v’tziveih v’nishkalei, chop up the wood and let
Gloria take it. So you know, if you're concerned about cutting into
the principal, what's the difference of those two cases? So the גמרא
Gemara says, אי משום הא לא קשיא, im mishum ha lo kashya,
if that was the point it wouldn't be difficult. I could say
we're concerned about cutting into, you know, I could say, זימנין דשמע
שני משכנתא ומקמי יובל, zimnin d’shama shneih mashkanta v’mikmi yovel, because Gloria
still benefits or I still benefit by buying the piece of land.
If I would sell the wood and give it to Gloria, she'd
make off like a bandit, she'd have all that cash immediately in
hand, and I'd get nothing out of it. If we buy a
plot of land and Gloria uses it, she gets it for the
next year, and even if the land will go back to Jenna
in ten years, I'll get it for nine years afterwards. So even
within the world that we're prepared to cut into the principal, there
are cases where it hurts me more and cases where it hurts
me less. Selling the wood, I totally lose out my asset. Buying
the land and letting Gloria use it and then I get to
use it for a few more years before the יובל, yovel, I
don't totally lose my asset. So that's obviously a better choice. אי
נמי דמטו זוזי ופרקי לה עד לא חמש שנין מקמי יובל, i
nami d’matu zuzei u’farik lah ad lo chamish shanin mikmi yovel,
or I might get the money together to pay off the loan
and get the plot of land before the יובל yovel hits. So
if Gloria has a plot of land, I still am in a
better situation. I'll get it back before the יובל yovel hits or
I could buy it back before the יובל yovel hits, whereas if
we sell the wood and give it to Gloria, I get nothing
out of that, I totally lose my asset. All right, so that's
important, you could in principle I'm never going to let you cut
into the owner's assets, or you could say I will let you
cut into the owner's assets, but we have to take maximum care
to protect the interests of the owners, to do it in the
way that's the best for them. the owner. Okay? So this ברייתא
can go either way, and this is the question of רב and
שמואל. I have an obligation to the owner. רב says you do
not cut into the owner's assets, שמואל says you are prepared to
cut into the owner's assets.
Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Now we get to a case of
boats. From donkeys to boats. השוכר את הספינה וטבעה לה בחצי הדרך.
hasocher et hasfina vetava lah bachatzi haderech.
You rented a boat and it sank in the middle of the
way with all of your wares on it. So basically the story
is that you know I have the wine to ship to Florida
there. Okay. David there's got the boat. Okay. So I put my
wine on his boat. I pay him $1,000 and we're going to
get it all the way to Florida. And that's different. That's actually
more like the renting the cab than renting the car. Because renting
the car is for a period of time. Okay here anyway it's
like I'm renting I'm you know I'm paying you not for a
period of time but for a journey. Okay. So I paid you
$1,000 to get it to Florida. The boat sinks off the shores
of South Carolina. I lose all my wine investment. You lose all
your boat investment. But now we still have to deal with how
about the money I owed you for the boat trip. Right. Do
I have to pay you halfway, not halfway? Similar type of a
question. Okay. Do you have to replace the boat, find me another
boat? But of course I don't have any wine left. So let's
talk about that. So okay. So רב נתן אומר, Rav Nosson omer,
so רב נתן Rav Nosson says נתן לא יטול ואם לא נתן
לא יתן. natan lo yitol veim lo natan lo yiten.
If I already paid David his fee, I cannot get it back.
If I haven't paid him his fee, I don't have to give
it. So it's like a type of המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה. hamotzi
mechavero alav haraaya. You know, each side equally lost out and nobody
has you know so anybody so whoever's in possession of the money
doesn't have an obligation to give it. The גמרא Gemara, is going
to try to understand so the גמרא Gemara, is going to try
to figure this out. היכי דמי? heichi dami? What's the case? אילימא
בספינה זו ויין סתם, ilima bisfina zo veyayin stam,
that I said I'm going to rent this boat and I will
load it up with wine. So now who when the boat sinks
is not able to fulfill the terms of the contract? David. He
doesn't have that boat. Okay. I can provide wine. I can pay
I can still get wine to ship for the rest of the
half of the way. Okay. I can do my half of what
the arrangement was because I just said wine, I didn't say this
wine. But you can't do your side of arrangement. You said this
boat. So
בספינה זו ויין סתם, bisfina zo veyayin stam, נתן אמאי לא יטול?
natan amai lo yitol? If I paid why can't I get my
money back? נימא ליה הב לי ספינתא, neima leh hav li sfinta,
give me a boat, a replacement boat, because you said a boat.
דאנא מייתינא חמרא, deana meitina chamra, I'll get some wine to ship
the rest of the way. At least in theory I can do
my half of it. I can get the wine. So you are
the one that can't live up to your terms of the agreement.
So therefore I don't have to pay you.
Okay. אלא בספינה סתם ויין זה. ela bisfina stam veyayin zeh. Fine.
Let's say it's a reverse case. David said a boat and I
said we're going to ship this wine. So now David says I'll
be prepared to replace the boat, I can in theory live up
to my terms of the agreement, I said a boat, I can
get you another boat. You though are not in a position to
to do the contract because you said this wine and you don't
have this wine anymore, it sank. So you're the one who can't
finish the agreement. Okay. אם לא נתן אמאי לא יתן? im lo
natan amai lo yiten? So in that case even if I didn't
pay why do I not have to pay? David is ready to
at least in theory do his side of the agreement and I'm
the one who has say who is not in a position to
go through with it. Okay. נימא ליה הב לי ההוא חמרא, neima
leh hav li hahu chamra, go get me that wine from the
bottom of the ocean. ואנא מייתינא ספינתא, veana meitina sfinta, and I'll
get a boat. Okay so it's very interesting. It's not really a
question of whether I will actually find wine that I want to
ship from South Carolina to Florida. The point is that at least
in theory right the one who said סתם stam whether it's the
one who in theory is is able to live up to their
terms of the agreement. The one who said זה zeh is unable
to. Okay and therefore that's the one although nobody was to blame
right but based on who's unable to live up that determine if
you can't live up then I don't have to pay you. If
I can't live up then I do have to pay you. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara. says like this. אמר רב פפא. amar Rav
Pappa. So that's if one said זה zeh and one said סתם.
stam. So obviously the next two cases are to look at is
that they either both said זה zeh or they both said סתם.
stam. What would be the case there? So אמר רב פפא לא
משכחת לה. amar Rav Pappa lo mashkachat lah. The case where one
doesn't have a claim against the other you know is אלא בספינה
זו ויין זה. ela bisfina zo veyayin zeh. When David said this
boat and I say this wine. In that case David says to
me you're not living up to your terms of the agreement. It's
impossible for you. And I say David you're you're not living up
to your terms. It's impossible for you. So since each one of
us can make the claim to the other you're to blame you
you can't live up to your terms. The point is המוציא מחבירו
עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav haraaya. Right. David if I haven't paid
David yet and he wants to come to me and ask me
to pay him I say sure go ahead bring me back that
boat and then I'll pay you because you said that boat. Okay.
If I've paid David and I want my money back David says
bring me back that wine and I'll give you your money back.
So because each one has a claim that the other one isn't
living up to the terms it's a type of המוציא מחבירו. hamotzi
mechavero. You can't get money out of anyone. Okay. But what if
they both said סתם? stam? Both said סתם stam is interesting. If
they both said סתם stam then in theory we could continue the
agreement. ment. You could go ahead and find another boat, I could
go ahead and find another wine. Okay, but probably neither of us
wants to bother at that stage. So what do we do at
that stage? אבל בספינה סתם ויין סתם חולקין. Aval b'sefinah stam v'yayin
stam cholkin. In that stage, we split, we pay for half, like
I pay for the half that was done and not for the
other half. Because if I want to say to you, you know,
I'm not going to pay for the other half because we didn't
get the whole way, you know what you'll say back to me?
Fine, bring the wine and I'll provide the boat for the rest
of the way. And if I'm prepared to bring the wine and
you bring the boat, fine, okay. But the point is that since,
you know, because in theory we're both able to go through with
it, but in practice neither of us wants to, so therefore it
basically winds up to be pay half. Okay, yes.
Is it, someone's paying in advance, aren't they paying for the completion
of a job?
Yeah, but what happens in this case exactly, of an אונס? ones?
Nobody is to blame, okay, and I mean, so that's exactly what
it's figuring out.
I know, it just seems that in some ways in my mind
it should be the person who got paid to complete the job,
it should be his responsibility, I don't know why.
Yeah, so you are, you're a freelance photographer, right? So if you
got paid to do a job and then in the middle of
the job something happened and all of your equipment broke or whatever,
like a big boulder fell on it, would you expect to get
no money?
I'm saying I should, somehow I feel like I should have to
complete the job.
Yeah, but you can't.
No, I mean I should have to get my,
oh, you mean this case where you say ספינה סתם? sefinah stam?
Oh, so that's
true, if I say, I am prepared to go to right now
the buy some more wine here in South Carolina and I want
the job done, then yes, you do have to provide another boat,
and if at that stage you can't provide another boat, I don't
have to pay you anything. Okay.
And he's already paid him, I guess.
Oh, it doesn't matter who has, right, right, at that stage right,
it doesn't matter who's in possession. The המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה Hamotzi
mechavero alav hara'ayah is when each one is equally to blame. Here
so, yeah, right.
Would they also sell the, like, let's say there's like, some of
the wine that are floating on the top or something, like one
barrel that...
Yeah, that's, yeah, well that would still be owned by the person
who owned the wine, but that wouldn't sort of change this agreement
which has to do with the whole sort of, you know, with
the whole load. Okay, so let's move on to the next case.
תנו רבנן: Tanu rabanan: השוכר את הספינה ופרקה בחצי הדרך. Hasocher et
hasefinah uparkah bachatzi haderech. Now
this is a case where you rent a boat and right there,
you know, it docked in South Carolina to load up new provisions,
and you actually say, you know what, forget it, I'm not going
all the way to Florida, I'm just going to take my wares
off right over here. Okay? So נותן לו שכרו של חצי הדרך.
Noten lo secharo shel chatzi haderech. You pay him only half the
way, ואין לו עליו אלא תרעומת. v'ein lo alav ela taromet. The
owner of the boat can't say, what the heck are you talking
about? Like I rigged the whole boat for the whole trip, I
was expecting the whole trip, you know? No, I only went half
the way, I'm done now, I'm getting out. Now of course if
you say that to a taxi driver, you know what, let me
out here, there's a lot of traffic, let me out here, you
only pay for half, right? But there's a little bit of a
difference there, right, because there it's not like, you know, it's not
like a decision to go on a big journey which requires losing
other opportunities, maybe making some investments, okay? So here it says you
pay him only half the way and the boat owner only has
a little bit, only has complaints. So the גמרא Gemara says once
again, היכי דמי? Heichi dami? What's the scenario? אילימא דקא משכח לאגורה,
Ilima d'ka mashkach l'agurah, if basically
I, the boat owner, can find here in South Carolina other people
who want to rent my services and bring their wares to
Florida, אמאי אית ליה תרעומת? amai it lei taromet? Why do I
even have anything to complain about? I'll just get another customer. ואי
דלא קא משכח לאגורה, V'ee d'lo ka mashkach l'agurah, and if I
can't find other customers, כולי אגרה בעי שלומי. kulei agrah bei shlumei.
David should have to pay me for the whole trip, right? I
gave up other opportunities, we made an arrangement for the whole trip,
okay, he's the one who's backing out now. It's sort of like,
you know, the owner backing out on the workers, right? So he
should have to pay me for the whole thing. So the גמרא
Gemara says no, לעולם דקא משכח לאגורה, Le'olam d'ka mashkach l'agurah, I
can actually find other customers. אלא אמאי אית ליה תרעומת? Ela amai
it lei taromet?
And that's why David doesn't have to pay me, because David says
to me, you'll find plenty of customers here in South Carolina to
go the rest of the way. So why do I have a
complaint? משום רפסתא דספינתא, Mishum rifsata d'sefinata,
because of the wear and tear of the boat. David's going to
schlepp all of his stuff off and then we're going to have
other people schlepp it all on, right? So there's more wear and
tear here switching customers in the middle. So the גמרא Gemara says,
oh, you could also say that I have to go and hustle
to find customers. אי הכי, Ee hachi, says the גמרא, Gemara if
that's true, טענא מעליא הוא וממונא אית ליה גביה. Ta'ana ma'alya hu
umamona it lei gabei.
For then David is really, is really causing me a loss, right?
There really is some depreciation or whatever. Why doesn't he have to
pay me? Right, even when I replace him, there was actually some
loss to me. אלא, says the גמרא, Gemara מאי תרעומת? mai taromet?
What is my complaint? משום שינוי דעתא, Mishum shinui da'ata,
because of a שינוי דעת. shinui da'at. Now what does שינוי דעת
shinui da'at mean? So תוספות Tosafot says what it means here is,
David is going to unload his stuff very carefully, one item at
a time, okay, white glove service or whatever, cause no wear and
tear. We're going to load up the new stuff also super carefully,
no wear and tear. But I still have a complaint. What's my
complaint? My complaint is I agreed to go with David, he's an
easygoing guy, I liked him as a customer. The next person I'm
going to get, who knows? What do I know? He's going to
be האקן מיר א טשייניק hocking me a tchainik for the whole
rest of the trip. He's a big complainer, he's a whatever. Okay,
so there I have a complaint. I didn't want to deal with
other customers I didn't know about. Okay, אי נמי אור ina mi
u-or לאשלי יתירא l-ashlei yeteira for for other extra ropes. Okay, which
basically, you know, maybe there's no, I'm going to have to buy
רש״י Rashi says, I'm going to have to buy more, you know,
rigging and ropes here. If I was at home, I would have
taken from my own stock. Here I have to buy, you know,
new stock. So so that's because the other guy maybe he's got
more wares, different wares requires different containers. Of course then the point
is again, so then why don't I really have to pay why
doesn't David have to pay me? That was a real expense. But
presumably here the point is that then I'm actually just buying more
assets for myself. So even though I would have preferred not to,
you know, it's still, you know, that's why it's sort of a
complaint, but a legitimate complaint. Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Now let's
look at another case. השוכר את החמור לרכוב עליה. Hasocher et hachamor
lirkov aleha.
So you rent a donkey to to what to to ride on
it. Did I skip a line by the way?
No? Okay. I think I'm thinking of something else. Hold on a
minute.
Yeah,
I did skip a line. I thought I did. Okay, nobody caught
it. Okay, so it was like this. אלא מאי פרקא, Ella mai
parka, so what does פרקא parka mean? To פרקא לטעוני דגבי. parka
l-te'unei d-gavei. Okay, which basically רש״י Rashi has another way of reading
it, but תוספות's Tosafot way of reading it means you unloaded the
wares on the boat itself and removed them, I described it, but
I didn't read the words in the גמרא. Gemara You unloaded the
wares on the boat itself and you removed them in a way
that caused no wear and tear. So we're doing it in a
scenario that causes no wear and tear and therefore I don't get
to get David to compensate me for the depreciation, for the wear
and tear. אלא מאי תרעומת, Ella mai taromet, so if there's no
wear and tear what's the complaint? The complaint is משום שינוי דעתא
mishum shinui da'ata because I have to deal with a new customer.
אי נמי ina mi לאשלי יתירא l-ashlei yeteira because I have to
buy new rigging. Okay. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, now next case. השוכר
את החמור לרכוב עליה. hasocher et hachamor lirkov aleha So you rent
a donkey to ride it. What's your rights about what you can
put on the donkey? שוכר מניח עליה כסותו ולגינתו, Sokher maniach aleha
ksuto v-lignuto,
I can put on it my garment and my water bottle, ומזונות
של אותו הדרך u-mezonot shel oto haderech and the food for the
whole journey. Okay. מכאן ואילך חמר מעכב עליו, Mikan va'eilach hammar me'akev
alav, the owner of the donkey can say, no no no, you
don't have rights to load anything more on your donkey. It's for
riding, it's not for carrying. So this is all you're allowed. חמר
מניח עליה שעורים ותבן ומזונותיו של אותו היום. Hammar maniach aleha se'orim
v-teven u-mezonotav shel oto hayom.
He puts on it, you know, grain and you know barley and
straw and the food for that day for the donkey presumably, the
donkey's food. So the גמרא Gemara. has a question. I get to
put on it my food for the whole journey. The donkey driver
only gets to put on it the donkey's food for that day.
Okay. מכאן ואילך שוכר מעכב עליו. Mikan va'eilach sokher me'akev alav. Any
more I the renter can say you don't get to put more
weight on the donkey. Okay. Because then it's slowing the donkey down.
היכי דמי? Heichi dami? What's the case? אי דשכיח
למזבן, I d-shchiach l-mizban, if we're stopping for the night where we'll
be you know at our stops you can buy food, חמר נמי
ליעכב, hammar nami l-akev,
so the donkey driver should stop me from putting the whole journey's
worth of food on it. You'll just buy it every stop. Of
course it's always more expensive there. ואי לא שכיח למזבן, V-i lo
shchiach l-mizban, and if it's not going to be available at our
stops to buy more food, שוכר נמי לא ליעכב, sokher nami lo
l-akev, why can I stop the donkey driver from putting more than
a day's worth? Which is another way of saying why do I
get to put the journey's worth of food and he only gets
to put the day's worth of food? So אמר רב פפא Amar
Rav Pappa לא צריכא דשכיח למיטרח ולמזבן מאבנא לאבנא, lo tzricha d-shchiach
l-mitrach u-lmizban me'avna l-avna,
from stop to stop you are it is going to be possible
to hustle and to find food to buy, but it requires effort.
So since it requires effort, so who has to put forth the
effort? חמר, Hammar, דרכיה למיטרח ולמזבן, darkei l-mitrach u-lmizban, you know he's
the worker. So it's expected that he's going to do the extra
hustling and the work. So if you're I'm hiring your services, you
only get a day's journey. When we stop you'll buy more food
for your donkey. Okay, you're my employee. Okay. שוכר, Sokher, the employer
essentially, the renter, לאו דרכיה למיטרח ולמזבן, lav darkei l-mitrach u-lmizban, I
like getting the royal treatment. Okay, I'm the one paying for you
know I'm not expecting to run around, I'm going to take my
food with me. Alright, so that's where I do I have based
on you know the norms, I have more rights than the donkey
driver, I have a right to do the whole journey's worth of
food, him only the day. Let's just finish. תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan
השוכר את החמור לרכוב עליה איש, ish, okay,
you rented it and you told me you know when you go
rent a car, right, if you want to sign up another driver,
you have to get the license plate, you guys drivers license, is
he under 24? Oh under 24, that's an extra fee. Okay, so
this is a similar type of a consideration. David rents a donkey
and he said that he was going to have a man ride
on it. לא ירכיב עליה אשה. Lo yirkiv aleha isha. I can't
have a woman ride on it. Now I did not see רש״י
Rashi or תוספות Tosafot describe why. Is it an assumption that women
are not as good drivers as men? Probably probably it's the opposite
is true when it comes to cars. I don't know. Anyway, or
is it the assumption that women ride side saddle and the donkey
isn't as... used to that, so maybe it's a little bit more
unusual for the donkey, a little bit more of a concern? אשה,
Isha, if we've contracted for a woman to ride on it, רוכב
עליה איש, Rochiv alei ish, then you know what, it's actually an
easier task for the donkey to have a man on top of
it. He rides on top like everyone else does, but if we
contracted for a man and you brought a woman, we're worried that
there's going to be a problem. אשה Isha once it was agreed
for a woman to ride on it, בין גדולה בין קטנה, Bein
gedola bein ktana, whether she's an adult or a minor, אפילו מעוברת
ואפילו מניקה, Afilu meuberes vaafilu menika, it doesn't matter like same way
if you said a man, doesn't matter young man, old man, woman
also doesn't matter, not only that whether she is even if she's
pregnant and even if she's nursing,
which might mean more weight, right? So I thought one person, now
you're going to put a pregnant person, nursing person, it's like when
you rent a when you have a seat for the airport, are
you allowed to take your baby with you? They don't charge more
for pregnant women, that I know though. Okay, so the גמרא asks
השתא מניקה אמרת מעוברת מיבעיא? Hashta menika amarta meuberes mibaya? If a
nursing woman can you know is included where it's actually a separate
baby, it's a separate person, right, of course a pregnant woman should
be included, that's all one person even if she weighs more. So
אמר פפא Amar Pappa no, מעוברת והיא מניקה. Meuberes vehi menika. No,
no, we mean pregnant and nursing. Okay, even that, even both of
them she can you know if she's both at the same time.
אמר אביי Amar Abaye says אביי Abaye
שמע מינה Shema mina from this the fact that it assumes that
a pregnant woman weighs more than a normal woman, like duh, from
this we can figure out אכרסא תקלא Akarsa tikla that something's weight
is in its the weight is in the stomach. What does this
mean? למאי נפקא מינה למקח וממכר Lemai nafka mina lemakach umimkar for
purchase. What רש"י says it means is this, you have a fish,
okay, and רש"י says it might have a lot of like you
know what it ate and the guts in its stomach might be
adding to the weight you know in a disproportionate way. So if
you're smart what you'll say is first gut the fish and then
let's weigh it, not weigh it before it's gutted, okay. But again,
the question is like what's the חידוש, Chidush, right? Of course something
that has something in its stomach has more weight. So I'll just
end by saying תוספות Tosafos says reads the גמרא in a slightly
different way, and תוספות Tosafos says that the גמרא actually was saying
the reverse, that a woman carrying an infant weighs less than a
pregnant woman. Why? Because a woman carrying an infant, the idea is
that the infant carries some of its own weight and the mother
supports some of its own weight, so that actually the גמרא is
saying the opposite, that something that's pregnant, a woman a pregnant woman
actually weighs more also because there's more fluid right for the source
for the baby. So I don't know if that's actually true whether
the net weight you're saying it's not so you don't know. After
a mother has given birth.
Yes, but there's no such thing as a baby doesn't hold up
its own guts, that's not what
well the mother supports its
weight, they're all on the donkey.
Right, I don't know. Anyway, that's what תוספות Tosafos says, okay, which
is an interesting flip on what the גמרא was saying.
It would be an interesting experiment like is it a day after
the baby was born?
That's what I'm asking. Does the mother with baby weigh less than
the pregnant mother the day after the mother's born?
Mother if the baby lose weight I
mean right and the mother and you're carrying all that fluids right.
Anyway, that's what תוספות Tosafos says is going on at the end
of the גמרא. Okay, new משנה tomorrow.